Chris, today I want to chat with
everyone about my thoughts on Cleo's
new album released mid-last month, "
GentleWoman." Those who know me well
should know that Cleo is my favorite
female singer—no, my favorite singer.
Actually, many people's first
impression upon hearing this album
might be that it's a "Mother 2.0,"
right? That was such a classic album
from 20 years ago. It might be because
the cover art looks a lot like "Mother,
" right? It also features Cleo holding
her newborn child. Then, secondly, it's
the texture of the songs as the album
begins, that piano intro, and Cleo's
voice, which might sound a bit like "
Mother." There’s another similarity,
which is the return of string
arrangements, right? Because the two
albums in between, "Gold" and "Ven,"
actually had smaller arrangements; they
didn't have such lavish strings. Now,
this "GentleWoman" has those lush
strings back, which is why many might
think it's "Mother 2.0." But as I kept
listening, and after hearing it many
times, I realized there are actually
many differences from "Mother."
Compared to "Mother," I feel the
overall listening experience of this
album—setting aside other musical
theories or other aspects—makes me
feel it is more aggressive. In "Mother,
" you hear Cleo reveal many vulnerable
parts of herself, but in this album, I
believe that vulnerability is gone.
Actually, you could already see her
becoming more and more resolute in the
"Gold" album. In this album, I think
you could say she has taken it a step
further. Second, I think this album
incorporates many other elements, for
example, some Latin influences like in
"Force of Love"—yes, "Force of Love,"
"Sentimental Love," and including "
Family Ties"—it has a lot of reggae
or Latin elements, if I remember
correctly. Now, the integration of
these elements is something you'd see
in her other persona, SA, but it's not
actually common on her own albums. Of
course, it’s much funkier in SA,
which I think is a conscious choice;
Cleo doesn't want to make her own
albums quite that funky. OK, the third
point I think is different is that many
songs on this album are like a full
extension of the second half of the
songs on "Mother." What do I mean by
that? Well, in "Mother," if you listen
to many of the songs, like "Music," for
instance, they are two-part structures.
The first part might have that piano or
ballad-like feel, but then the latter
part becomes a little different. I feel
like this album often extends that
latter part; it doesn't piece together
songs of completely different styles
like it did in Mother, right? For
instance, take the song "Smiles Are Not
the Same"; if it were in Mother, these
two songs might have been combined,
right? Because the transition between
them is indeed very smooth, but in this
album they are separated, so I think
that's a structural change. And the
most, most important point is that I
don't think this is a very healing
album; many people might equate Cleo
with healing, or Mother with healing. I
think that's perfectly fine. But in
this album, I don't feel like she
really wanted to create a healing vibe.
However, her voice is very healing;
when you listen to her tone, including
the textures in her arrangements, it
makes you feel that healing sensation.
But the overall message she wants to
convey, I don't think it's very healing
. I feel like many songs in Mother were
self-dialogues, written for herself.
There are some songs where, even though
she writes "you," in this album I feel
the "you" is truly addressed to people
around her; her own agency feels
stronger, as if she is telling those
around her, "Okay, I think you should
do this, I think you should do that."
Or else, the subject is God. Yes, for
this album, I think there are actually
many more religious elements; it's not
just some gospel-style harmonies, but
also the themes, from the first song "I
Only Look to You" to the end with "To
You," it's really mostly about God.
Overall, I think this album is a
synthesis; it takes Cleo's content from
Mother, from Gospel, from Haven, and
even some older stuff, and somehow
fuses it all together. If I hadn't
heard Mother, I might give this album a
ten. But perhaps because of Mother and
because I've heard so many Cleo songs,
the album doesn't really offer that
much new, so I probably would give it
an eight. I think it's still—well,
even if it doesn't have much new, it is
definitely very, very good, beautifully
produced, and Cleo's voice is
invincible, so it's a great album. I
wonder what you all think? Feel free to
share your favorite songs from this
album too, okay? Peace.